<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>entityframework on Always Developing</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/tags/entityframework/</link><description>Recent content in entityframework on Always Developing</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://always-developing.github.io/tags/entityframework/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>EF Core 6 column order</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/28-ef-column-order/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/28-ef-column-order/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop The Column attribute, as well as the new HasColumnOrder fluent API can be used to determine the specifically order of sequence of columns in the table.
Configurations previously In previous version of Entity Framework Core (EF) the order in which the columns were defined on the entity, where the order in which they were created on the table
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 public class Song { public string Artist { get; set; } public int YearReleased { get; set; } public int Id { get; set; } public int LengthInSeconds { get; set; } public string Name { get; set; } } The Up method migration created to create the table would look as below.</description></item><item><title>Entity Framework Core interceptors</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/24-efcore-interceptors/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/24-efcore-interceptors/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop Entity Framework Core has the concept of interceptors which allow for the insertion of custom logic during the query execution process.
There a number of real world applications for the functionality, for example:
Caching and retrieval of data Logging query or diagnostics information under certain conditions Modifying the query parameters, such as the timeout under certain conditions Interceptor structure Creating an interceptor is straight forward - a class is created which implements the abstract class DbCommandInterceptor, and then overrides the required relevant method(s).</description></item><item><title>EF Core 6 EntityTypeConfiguration Attribute</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/21-ef-core6-entitytypeconfig/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/21-ef-core6-entitytypeconfig/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop A new attribute called EntityTypeConfiguration was introduced in Entity Framework 6, which allows for easier configuration of custom entity configurations.
Let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at how is simplifies the configuration of an entity.
Configurations previously There are a number of steps performed when manually configuring an entity using Entity Framework Core (EF).
Note: The entity structure below is not optimized or suitable for a production system, it is used just for sample purposes</description></item><item><title>Dynamic Context (for Entity Framework Core)</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/11-2020-dynamic-context/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 03:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/11-2020-dynamic-context/</guid><description>The problem Entity Framework Core is a great go-to ORM for .NET, for any type of application provides almost all the functionality required to do successful database access out the box.
However, there are two use cases, specifically with regards to retrieval of data, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t cater for - this post and the accompanying code sample/NuGet package attempts to provides solutions for these use cases.
First, the setup - an EF DbContext which has one DbSet, for storing Blogs (the below is a standard DbContext configuration):</description></item><item><title>Roslyn Analyzer - tips and tricks (Part 5)</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-extra/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 05:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-extra/</guid><description>All posts in the series:
Part 1: Roslyn Analyzer - explained Part 2: Roslyn Analyzer - writing an analyzer
Part 3: Roslyn Analyzer - writing a code fix
Part 4: Roslyn Analyzer - testing an analyzer and code fix
Part 5: Roslyn Analyzer - tips and tricks (this post)
All code in the posts, including the sample project and working analyzer and code fix are available on Github.
Tips and tricks This post contains a list of tips and tricks, work-around&amp;rsquo;s and other bits of (what I find) useful information to aid in developing analyzers.</description></item><item><title>Roslyn Analyzer - testing an analyzer and code fix (Part 4)</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-test/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Nov 2021 04:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-test/</guid><description>All posts in the series:
Part 1: Roslyn Analyzer - explained Part 2: Roslyn Analyzer - writing an analyzer
Part 3: Roslyn Analyzer - writing a code fix
Part 4: Roslyn Analyzer - testing an analyzer and code fix (this post)
Part 5: Roslyn Analyzer - tips and tricks
All code in the posts, including the sample project and working analyzer and code fix are available on Github.
Analyzer unit test introduction The previous posts in the series detail how to write an analyzer and code fix.</description></item><item><title>Roslyn Analyzer - writing the code fix (Part 3)</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-code-fix/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Nov 2021 03:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-code-fix/</guid><description>All posts in the series:
Part 1: Roslyn Analyzer - explained Part 2: Roslyn Analyzer - writing an analyzer
Part 3: Roslyn Analyzer - writing a code fix (this post)
Part 4: Roslyn Analyzer - testing an analyzer and code fix
Part 5: Roslyn Analyzer - tips and tricks
All code in the posts, including the sample project and working analyzer and code fix are available on Github.
Code fix introduction As detailed in the previous post in the series, now that there is a working analyzer which accurately reports diagnostic information to Roslyn, the next step is to write the code fix to resolve the diagnostic.</description></item><item><title>Roslyn Analyzer - writing the analyzer (Part 2)</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-write/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-write/</guid><description>All posts in the series:
Part 1: Roslyn Analyzer - explained Part 2: Roslyn Analyzer - writing an analyzer (this post)
Part 3: Roslyn Analyzer - writing a code fix
Part 4: Roslyn Analyzer - testing an analyzer and code fix
Part 5: Roslyn Analyzer - tips and tricks
All code in the posts, including the sample project and working analyzer and code fix are available on Github.
Analyzer introduction To recap from the previous post in the series, an analyzer is a piece of code which inspects code (C# or Visual Basic) during design and compile time, and based on the results of the inspection, can trigger a diagnostic as an Error, Warning or as Information.</description></item><item><title>Roslyn Analyzer - explained (Part 1)</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-explained/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2021 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-explained/</guid><description>Series introduction This is a a five part series exploring the Roslyn analyzer and code fix functionality, how to successfully write and test a custom analyzer, as well as some useful tips and tricks for writing analyzers.
All posts in the series:
Part 1: Roslyn Analyzer - explained (this post)
Part 2: Roslyn Analyzer - writing an analyzer
Part 3: Roslyn Analyzer - writing a code fix
Part 4: Roslyn Analyzer - testing an analyzer and code fix</description></item></channel></rss>