<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>entityframeworkcore on Always Developing</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/tags/entityframeworkcore/</link><description>Recent content in entityframeworkcore on Always Developing</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 01:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://always-developing.github.io/tags/entityframeworkcore/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Soft deletes with EF global filters</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/04/26-ef-soft-delete/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/04/26-ef-soft-delete/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop Entity Framework Core&amp;rsquo;s global filter functionality can be used to a apply a filter automatically to all queries on a dbSet.
This is especially useful when dealing with soft delete functionality, where the data is not removed from the database table, but instead just marked as deleted (or archived or retired etc)
Setup Consider a Song class and IRetirable interface which is as follows:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 public interface IRetirable { public bool IsRetired { get; set; } } [Table(&amp;#34;Song&amp;#34;)] public class Song : IRetirable { public int Id { get; set; } public string Name { get; set; } public string Artist { get; set; } public int YearReleased { get; set; } public int LengthInSeconds { get; set; } public bool IsRetired { get; set; } public override string ToString() { return $&amp;#34;Song `{Name}` by &amp;#39;{Artist} released &amp;#34; + $&amp;#34;in &amp;#39;{YearReleased}&amp;#39; and is &amp;#39;{LengthInSeconds}&amp;#39; seconds long&amp;#34;; } } Without global filters Every time the Song dbset is queried, only active records (records which have the IsRetired field set to false) should be returned.</description></item><item><title>Entity Framework Core interceptors</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/24-efcore-interceptors/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/24-efcore-interceptors/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop Entity Framework Core has the concept of interceptors which allow for the insertion of custom logic during the query execution process.
There a number of real world applications for the functionality, for example:
Caching and retrieval of data Logging query or diagnostics information under certain conditions Modifying the query parameters, such as the timeout under certain conditions Interceptor structure Creating an interceptor is straight forward - a class is created which implements the abstract class DbCommandInterceptor, and then overrides the required relevant method(s).</description></item><item><title>EF Core 6: GroupBy enhancements</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/04-ef-core6-groupby/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/04-ef-core6-groupby/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop The GroupBy support in Entity Framework Core 6 got an update, and has made things a lot easier.
In short, the following is now supported:
Translate GroupBy followed by FirstOrDefault (or similar) over a group Supports selecting the top N results from a group Expands navigation&amp;rsquo;s after the GroupBy operator has been applied Examples Setup In all the example below the setup is very simple - a single Song entity and corresponding database table.</description></item></channel></rss>