<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>DI on Always Developing</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/tags/di/</link><description>Recent content in DI on Always Developing</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 01:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://always-developing.github.io/tags/di/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dependency Injection with Func and delegates</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/03/07-di-func-delegate/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/03/07-di-func-delegate/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop When requiring to abstract and inject a simple single method interface using dependency injection (DI), its possible to instead use a Func&amp;lt;&amp;gt; or a Delegate instead.
Examples Suppose we want to inject the date time using dependency injection, instead of using DateTime.Now or DateTimeOffSet.Now.
There are a few reasons to do this:
DateTime.Now returns the current system datetime. This does not account for users in different regions, daylight savings etc (this is a complex subject, see the NodaTime reference below for additional information) The current datetime is an external dependency - best practice is for all external dependencies to be abstracted, so that they can be mocked and successfully unit tested There are a number of ways to tackle this requirement.</description></item><item><title>Multiple implementations of same interface - the options</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/multiple-implementations/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Nov 2021 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/multiple-implementations/</guid><description>The challenge Consider a scenario where the requirement is to upload a file to an online provider (AWS S3, Azure Blob or a FTP site in the examples below), where the provider can be easily changed (either dynamically at runtime, or easily with minimal code changes), with the possibility additional providers being added in future.
To make use of dependency injection, a generic interface is created, IFileUploader, along with three implementations AWSUploader, AzureUploader and FTPUploader.</description></item></channel></rss>