<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>sql on Always Developing</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/tags/sql/</link><description>Recent content in sql on Always Developing</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 01:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://always-developing.github.io/tags/sql/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Introduction to the SQL MERGE</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/05/25-sql-merged/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/05/25-sql-merged/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop The SQL MERGE statement can be used to perform an INSERT, UPDATE and/or DELETE all in one statement.
This post is just an introduction and does not address any performance issues or other bugs with the statement. See here (although out of date) for a list of potential bugs.
Example In the below examples, we have a main Order table, which stores orders in our e-commerce system.</description></item><item><title>Using SQL Server's OFFSET and FETCH</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/03/17-sql-offset-fetch/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/03/17-sql-offset-fetch/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop SQL Server has two keywords available, OFFSET and FETCH which can be used to limit the number of rows returned by a query.
This functionality has been available in SQL Server 2012 and later, and Azure SQL Database.
Limiting rows returned The OFFSET keyword can be used independently or in conjunction with the FETCH keyword, which cannot be used in isolation.
OFFSET: determines how many rows to skip at the start of the dataset FETCH: determines how many rows to return, after the OFFSET rows have been skipped Whether using only OFFSET or OFFSET + FETCH, in both situations, the ORDER BY clause is required.</description></item></channel></rss>