<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>with on Always Developing</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/tags/with/</link><description>Recent content in with on Always Developing</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 01:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://always-developing.github.io/tags/with/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Cancel a task with OperationCanceledException</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/04/01-task-cancellationtoken/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/04/01-task-cancellationtoken/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop When cancelling tasks using a CancellationTokenSource, rather than do a soft cancellation, an OperationCanceledException should be thrown.
Cancellation Token A quick summary of cancellation tokens - they &amp;ldquo;enable cooperative cancellation between threads, thread pool work items or Task objects&amp;rdquo;.
Basically cancellation tokens are instantiated outside a particular thread, and then passed into the thread, to allow for cancellation from outside the thread.
Examples In each of the below examples, there is a &amp;ldquo;long&amp;rdquo; running process which runs for 10 seconds.</description></item><item><title>Anonymous types and with keyword</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/03/31-anon-with/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/03/31-anon-with/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop The with keyword can be used to create a new instance of an anonymous type where one of more properties have new values.
Anonymous types First off, a brief explanation of anonymous types. Anonymous types are a way to encapsulate a set of read only properties into a single object without explicitly defining a type. The type name is generated internally by the compiler and the type of each property is inferred by the compiler.</description></item></channel></rss>