<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>c# on Always Developing</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/tags/c#/</link><description>Recent content in c# on Always Developing</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://always-developing.github.io/tags/c#/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Garbage collection configuration</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/18-gc-variables/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/18-gc-variables/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop There are a number of settings related to the .NET garbage collector (GC) which can be set at runtime using a variety of methods. Generally these do not need to be manually configured, but can be changed from the default to tweak and optimize performance of the application.
Configurations The settings which can be configured are listed below (more detailed information can be found under references section below)</description></item><item><title>Using with IDisposable</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/17-using-idisposable/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/17-using-idisposable/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop To make use of the using statement in C#, all you need to do is implement the IDisposable interface on a class.
The using statement provides a convenient syntax to ensure the correct use of IDisposable objects. The object in question will exists for the scope of the using and then automatically be disposed once out of scope.
This functionality can also be leveraged to create scoped helper instances for certain use cases.</description></item><item><title>Task.WaitAsync in .NET6</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/16-task-wait-async/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/16-task-wait-async/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop A new method on Task called WaitAsync was introduced in .NET6. This method allows for waiting on a Task for a specific period of time before throwing a timeout exception.
On the surface, this might not seem very useful, but lets look at some examples to see how this new method can be leveraged.
The issue Long running processes Suppose we have a long running method which returns a Task - in the below example we are simulating a download process which takes 5 seconds</description></item><item><title>Aliases with global using directives</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/15-global-using-directives/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/15-global-using-directives/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop With the introduction of global usings in C#10, it is now also possible to defined a global alias to have a shortcut to a specific type, across an entire project.
Global usings A quick intro to global usings - In C#10 the concept of global usings was introduced. It allows for a using statement to be prefixed with global, which then includes that using in all files automatically when compiled.</description></item><item><title>Filtering try-catch statement</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/14-exceptions-when/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/14-exceptions-when/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop It is possible to filter the catch portion of the try-catch statement, as well as catch multiple exceptions at the same time using the C# when keyword.
Multiple exceptions In our use case, there are two exception types we are particularly interested in IndexOutOfRangeException and DivideByZeroException.
If either of these exceptions occur, we want to log the exception, and carry on with the workflow. However if any other exception occurs, it should be logged and re-thrown to be handled higher up the call stack.</description></item><item><title>Extract calling method metadata with C#</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/11-caller-metadata/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/11-caller-metadata/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop As part of the C# System.Runtime assembly, there are a number of Attributes which can be used to get information about the caller of a method.
The pattern for usage is the same for all attributes. To extract the metadata when a method is called, the following needs to be done:
A new parameter needs to be added to the method (the type of the parameter depends on the attribute, see examples below) The new parameter must have a default value The new parameter must be decorated with the relevant Attribute Attributes Lets look at a few examples.</description></item><item><title>C# Channels - Produce &amp; Consume data</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/10-channels/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/10-channels/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop Today we dive into a little-known C# feature, I&amp;rsquo;d previously never heard about called Channels.
So what is a channel? - In short, a channel is a feature which allows for passing of data between a producer and consumer(s). It is an efficient, thread-safe queuing mechanism.
Usage The examples set out below are very simple, and do not reflect a real world scenario. They have eben kept as minimal as possible to display the core concepts of the Channel.</description></item><item><title>Performant logging with LoggerMessageAttribute</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/09-logger-message-attribute/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/09-logger-message-attribute/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop .NET6 introduced a new attribute called LoggerMessageAttribute, which leverages source generators and is designed to deliver a highly useable and performant logging solution.
It works by using source generators, triggered at compile time by the presence of LoggerMessageAttribute to generate the additional source code. This solution, due to the compile time generation, is able to eliminate performance hits, such as boxing, temporary memory allocation as well as copies which enables it to be typically considerably faster than the existing run time logging methods.</description></item><item><title>Scheduling with GitHub Actions</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/08-github-action-schedule/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/08-github-action-schedule/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop A GitHub Action can be configured to executed on a set schedule, and it&amp;rsquo;s as simple as adding a line to the workflow YAML using Cron syntax.
As part of the development of this blog, there was a requirement to execute an Action on a schedule - which turned out to be easier than anticipated.
Cron Quick intro to Cron syntax - if you are already familiar with this you can jump straight to how to implement in workflow YAML</description></item><item><title>C# ValueTuple</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/07-valuetuple/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/07-valuetuple/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop You may have heard of C# the Tuple type, but there is also a ValueTuple type available, which has existed in C# since .NET 4.7!
The post will will take a brief look at the Tuple type and compare its functionality to that of the ValueTuple type.
Tuple Tuple usage A Tuple is a data structure which has a specific number and sequence of elements. The data structure can contain up to 8 elements, but if more are required, nested tuple objects can be leveraged in the 8th element to extent the number of elements.</description></item><item><title>EF Core 6: GroupBy enhancements</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/04-ef-core6-groupby/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/04-ef-core6-groupby/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop The GroupBy support in Entity Framework Core 6 got an update, and has made things a lot easier.
In short, the following is now supported:
Translate GroupBy followed by FirstOrDefault (or similar) over a group Supports selecting the top N results from a group Expands navigation&amp;rsquo;s after the GroupBy operator has been applied Examples Setup In all the example below the setup is very simple - a single Song entity and corresponding database table.</description></item><item><title>Use IOptions&lt;> for application configuration</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/03-ioptions/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/03-ioptions/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop Instead of trying to manually setup the dependency injection container with configuration from the, for example, appsettings.json file, use the built in .NET functionality and use the IOptions interface instead - and get IOptionsSnapshot and IOptionsMonitor for free!
This post won&amp;rsquo;t go into details around the options pattern specifically, but it&amp;rsquo;s the recommended approach when dealing with application settings as it enables the application to adhere to two important software architecture principles:</description></item><item><title>C# Records - the rundown</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/02-record-intro/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/02-record-intro/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop Heard about the new feature of C# called records, but not entirely sure whats its all about? Here&amp;rsquo;s the brief overview.
Records:
Are reference types - just like normal classes Have equality based on value and not memory - unlike normal classes Are immutable (sometimes) - unlike normal classes Can be inherited - just like normal classes Internally the compiler converts will convert a record declaration to a specialized class, so that it conforms to the above.</description></item><item><title>Use the ILogger IsEnabled method</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/01-ilogger-isenabled/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/dailydrop/2022/02/01-ilogger-isenabled/</guid><description>Daily Knowledge Drop When performing logging using the ILogger interface, to have more effective memory usage, ensure to check if logging is enabled for the relevant log level before calling the log method.
For example:
❌ Don&amp;rsquo;t do this: 1 logger.LogWarning(&amp;#34;Value is outside expected range of &amp;#39;{0}&amp;#39; to &amp;#39;{1}&amp;#39;&amp;#34;, 100, 120);
✅ Do this: 1 2 3 4 if(logger.IsEnabled(LogLevel.Warning)) { logger.LogWarning(&amp;#34;Value is outside expected range of &amp;#39;{0}&amp;#39; to &amp;#39;{1}&amp;#39;&amp;#34;, 100, 120); }</description></item><item><title>Structured logging - an introduction</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/01-2022-structured-logging/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 03:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/01-2022-structured-logging/</guid><description>Introduction This post will give an introduction to structured logging, why its needed and should be used. It will also go into detail how to implement and customize the output using Serilog.
Default .NET Logging Before looking at structured logging, we&amp;rsquo;ll take a look at the default .NET logging implementation.
The default logger can be utilized by injecting ILogger&amp;lt;CategoryName&amp;gt; into the relevant constructor. The ILogger&amp;lt;&amp;gt; interface and its implementation are registered automatically with the .</description></item><item><title>Git workflows - explained</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/01-2022-git-workflow/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 03:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/01-2022-git-workflow/</guid><description>Introduction This post will give a brief introduction and explanation to Git and Git workflows, and then go into detail for the most prominent workflows (in my experience), when to use them, as well as the main pros and cons of each approach.
Background Git introduction For those unfamiliar, Git (as defined on git-scm.com) is a free and open source distributed version control system, designed to handle everything from small to very large projects with speed and efficiency.</description></item><item><title>Azure Devops Symbol Server - a how to guide</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/12-2021-devops-symbol-server/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 03:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/12-2021-devops-symbol-server/</guid><description>Symbol server explained What are symbols? When building a .NET project, symbol files (generally files with the extension of .pdb) are automatically created by the compiler. These symbol files contain metadata information about the source code (indexes, function names, line numbers, etc) and are used when debugging and stepping through code, by linking the debugger (e.g. Visual Studio) to the source code.
Generally, these symbol files are only available when developing locally, and building a project in debug configuration - that is, unless they are uploaded to a symbol server.</description></item><item><title>Dynamic Context (for Entity Framework Core)</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/11-2020-dynamic-context/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 03:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/11-2020-dynamic-context/</guid><description>The problem Entity Framework Core is a great go-to ORM for .NET, for any type of application provides almost all the functionality required to do successful database access out the box.
However, there are two use cases, specifically with regards to retrieval of data, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t cater for - this post and the accompanying code sample/NuGet package attempts to provides solutions for these use cases.
First, the setup - an EF DbContext which has one DbSet, for storing Blogs (the below is a standard DbContext configuration):</description></item><item><title>Roslyn Analyzer - tips and tricks (Part 5)</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-extra/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 05:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-extra/</guid><description>All posts in the series:
Part 1: Roslyn Analyzer - explained Part 2: Roslyn Analyzer - writing an analyzer
Part 3: Roslyn Analyzer - writing a code fix
Part 4: Roslyn Analyzer - testing an analyzer and code fix
Part 5: Roslyn Analyzer - tips and tricks (this post)
All code in the posts, including the sample project and working analyzer and code fix are available on Github.
Tips and tricks This post contains a list of tips and tricks, work-around&amp;rsquo;s and other bits of (what I find) useful information to aid in developing analyzers.</description></item><item><title>Roslyn Analyzer - testing an analyzer and code fix (Part 4)</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-test/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Nov 2021 04:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-test/</guid><description>All posts in the series:
Part 1: Roslyn Analyzer - explained Part 2: Roslyn Analyzer - writing an analyzer
Part 3: Roslyn Analyzer - writing a code fix
Part 4: Roslyn Analyzer - testing an analyzer and code fix (this post)
Part 5: Roslyn Analyzer - tips and tricks
All code in the posts, including the sample project and working analyzer and code fix are available on Github.
Analyzer unit test introduction The previous posts in the series detail how to write an analyzer and code fix.</description></item><item><title>Roslyn Analyzer - writing the code fix (Part 3)</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-code-fix/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Nov 2021 03:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-code-fix/</guid><description>All posts in the series:
Part 1: Roslyn Analyzer - explained Part 2: Roslyn Analyzer - writing an analyzer
Part 3: Roslyn Analyzer - writing a code fix (this post)
Part 4: Roslyn Analyzer - testing an analyzer and code fix
Part 5: Roslyn Analyzer - tips and tricks
All code in the posts, including the sample project and working analyzer and code fix are available on Github.
Code fix introduction As detailed in the previous post in the series, now that there is a working analyzer which accurately reports diagnostic information to Roslyn, the next step is to write the code fix to resolve the diagnostic.</description></item><item><title>Roslyn Analyzer - writing the analyzer (Part 2)</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-write/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-write/</guid><description>All posts in the series:
Part 1: Roslyn Analyzer - explained Part 2: Roslyn Analyzer - writing an analyzer (this post)
Part 3: Roslyn Analyzer - writing a code fix
Part 4: Roslyn Analyzer - testing an analyzer and code fix
Part 5: Roslyn Analyzer - tips and tricks
All code in the posts, including the sample project and working analyzer and code fix are available on Github.
Analyzer introduction To recap from the previous post in the series, an analyzer is a piece of code which inspects code (C# or Visual Basic) during design and compile time, and based on the results of the inspection, can trigger a diagnostic as an Error, Warning or as Information.</description></item><item><title>Roslyn Analyzer - explained (Part 1)</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-explained/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2021 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/analyzer-explained/</guid><description>Series introduction This is a a five part series exploring the Roslyn analyzer and code fix functionality, how to successfully write and test a custom analyzer, as well as some useful tips and tricks for writing analyzers.
All posts in the series:
Part 1: Roslyn Analyzer - explained (this post)
Part 2: Roslyn Analyzer - writing an analyzer
Part 3: Roslyn Analyzer - writing a code fix
Part 4: Roslyn Analyzer - testing an analyzer and code fix</description></item><item><title>Multiple implementations of same interface - the options</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/multiple-implementations/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Nov 2021 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/multiple-implementations/</guid><description>The challenge Consider a scenario where the requirement is to upload a file to an online provider (AWS S3, Azure Blob or a FTP site in the examples below), where the provider can be easily changed (either dynamically at runtime, or easily with minimal code changes), with the possibility additional providers being added in future.
To make use of dependency injection, a generic interface is created, IFileUploader, along with three implementations AWSUploader, AzureUploader and FTPUploader.</description></item><item><title>Useful Visual Studio keyboard shortcuts</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/vs-keyboard-shortcuts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/vs-keyboard-shortcuts/</guid><description>Why learn keyboard shortcuts? So I confess I have no empirical evidence to backup the up to 20% more productive claim. That number is just made up, but with years of experience on my side, it honestly feels fairly accurate to me!
Having often been involved in assisting, troubleshooting and debugging code with fellow developers, it is apparent that the developers which are familiar with their IDE, and make use of the shortcuts, generally (but not always!</description></item><item><title>C# String vs string</title><link>https://always-developing.github.io/p/string-vs-string/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2021 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://always-developing.github.io/p/string-vs-string/</guid><description>What&amp;rsquo;s the issue? When working with strings in C# one can either use String (uppercase) or string (lowercase) and in both cases the code will compile and execute.
Explicitly typed string variables can be done in either of the following ways:
string variable = &amp;#34;Always Developing&amp;#34;; String variable = &amp;#34;Always Developing&amp;#34;; Or when invoking string related methods, both of the following examples are valid:
string variable = string.Format(&amp;#34;Always Developing using {0}&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;C#&amp;#34;); String variable = String.</description></item></channel></rss>